<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of sure comfort preached at the funerall of Master Robert Keylwey Esquire, at Exton in Rutland, the 18. of Marche 1580. By Anthonie Anderson preacher, and Parson of Medburne in Leicestershiere.</title>
            <author>Anderson, Anthony, d. 1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19277</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 569</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108524</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844182</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844182</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8971</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19277)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8971)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 165:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of sure comfort preached at the funerall of Master Robert Keylwey Esquire, at Exton in Rutland, the 18. of Marche 1580. By Anthonie Anderson preacher, and Parson of Medburne in Leicestershiere.</title>
                  <author>Anderson, Anthony, d. 1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>87, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Middleton, dwelling in Fleetstreete at the signe of the Falcon,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8971:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8971:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sermon of <hi>ſure Comfort, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched</hi>
               </hi> at the Funerall of <hi>Master Robert Keylwey</hi> Eſquire, at Exton in Rutland, the 18. of Marche 1580.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Anthonie Anderſon Preacher, and Parſon of</hi> Medburne <hi>in Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterſhiere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by H. Middleton, dwelling in Fleetſtreete at the ſigne of the Falcon. <hi>ANNO</hi> 1581.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8971:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:8971:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON OF ſure comfort, preached at the Funerall of Maiſter <hi>Robert Keylway</hi> Eſquier, the 18. day of March. 1580.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>As we are aſſembled in the name of our good God, ſo let vs pray for his vniuerſall Church, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The text.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Bleſſed and holy is hee that hath part in the firſt reſurrection: for on ſuch the ſeconde death hath no power: but they ſhall bee the Prieſtes of God and Chriſt, and ſhall raigne with him a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeare. <bibl>Apocalips. 20.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath béene from aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time receiued, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie long vſed in the Church of God (right worſhipfull and Chriſtian audience) at the Funerals of the godly to haue the worde preached to the people: Not thereby to profite the deade (which no way after life can chaunge this depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſtate) but by it to inſtruct the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8971:3"/> that they may learne to die in the Lorde: and ſo reſt from the labour of ſinne and hell. And why may not the godly preacher, take occaſion at fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls to preach the worde of God? Nay: why ſhoulde they omitte any occaſion? but rather with Chriſt and his Apoſtles waite oportunitie to preach the worde, whenſoeuer the people be gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether? So Chriſt at Ieruſalem, Iohn in the wilderneſſe,<note place="margin">Iohn. 7. &amp;c. Math. 3.1. Mar. 1.45. Act. 17.22.</note> and Paul in Mars ſtréete preached the worde, where and in what place the people were aſſembled. The fathers likewiſe of the Church, of auncient time, haue at ſuch aſſemblies, taken occaſion to teach the liuing, euen when the funeralles were ſolemnized ouer the deade. Whereby it was, that thoſe men did not only benefit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Churh, during their liues, but euen their corps (as it were) did afforde a finall benefite to the ſame, at their departure to the earth. And though the Papiſtes haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed much this ſacred vſe, ſo as, at this day, ſome vſe it and ſuppoſe it, rather to benefite the dead, then ſéeking to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the liuing thereby: yet is this no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why we ſhould abſtaine from food, or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8971:3"/> our parentes ſhoulde foreſlow, to féed vs with the bread of life, bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemies of God haue abuſed it. Let vs then looke vpon this heauenly bread, which God (in mercie) by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> occaſion of this chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corps here preſent, hath new, in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of mine endeuour, offered vnto you. It is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable conſolation to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, ſpoken, and commanded to be written to them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould not be ſwallowed vp, in the ſorowes of ſharpe perſecution, and tyrannie of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt: Or be beaten from the anchor of hope in God, whileſt they are accurſed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world: or be driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to diſpaire vnder the croſſe, by the multitude of afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: but ſhould aſſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, of his loue towards them, &amp; of their eſtate in him, howſoeuer the malignaunt mindes of wicked men ſhould bend their force a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
            <q>Bleſſed and holy is he &amp;c.</q>
            <p>This ſcripture compriſeth a reſolute aunſwere, to that often aſked matter: namely, who is he that is truly bleſſed? &amp; what it is to bée bleſſed indéed. In an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere whereof, the ſpirite of God obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8971:4"/> this order. Firſt he declareth who they bée which be truely bleſſed. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly he doth elegantly ſet downe the condition and ſtate of them, which are ſo bleſſed.</p>
            <p>Touching the firſt: Who is bleſſed? he aunſwereth, <hi>Bleſſed is he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath part in the firſt reſurrection.</hi> Concerning the ſeconde: And what is their bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? He faith, <hi>For on ſuch the ſeconde death ſhal haue no power: but they ſhal be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſtes of God &amp; of Chriſt, &amp; ſhall raigne with him</hi> 1000. <hi>yeares,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>for euer.</hi> That we may take ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent profite of this Godly labour, let vs well obſerue the text:</p>
            <q>Beſſed is he that hath part, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>There hath béene no ſtate ſo accurſed, but the ſame hath deſired to be bleſſed: Nor any people ſo ſottiſh, that haue not, in cauſe of happy deſire, ſought after fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie. But ſuch as the diſpoſitions of the perſons were, ſuch for the moſt part, was their ſuppoſall of felicitie.<note place="margin">Symonides</note> Some ſort ſuppoſed it an happie thing to bée beautifull and braue.<note place="margin">Pindarus.</note> Some other dée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med happineſſe, to conſiſt onely in rule and dignitie: And therefore haue tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8971:4"/> with hazarde, their ſoules to Hell, atchiuing by wicked practizes ſome ſtately ſeates in earth.<note place="margin">Ariſtot.</note> Some haue ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ciuill honeſtie, to be the habite of true felicitie, and hauing obteined a faire courſe therein, haue onely reſted there, as in the chaire of heauenly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe. But others more lewde, haue ſonke themſelues to hell:<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> with gaping after earthly treaſure, haue theſaured to themſelues in déede, the malediction of God, againſt the day of wrath. Of this ſort was that Diues, in the 12. of Luke, and likewiſe his companion,<note place="margin">Luke. 12.</note> in the 16. of the ſame.<note place="margin">Luke. 16.</note> In whoſe earthly beatitude, appeare theſe deadly miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: Namely, in obtaining riches a greedie deſire, and in poſſeſſing them, a double miſchiefe. To themſelues, they did abounde in great prodigalitie, but vnto all other they were impriſoned in the déepe dungeon of needleſſe nigardie. For the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues they gathered ſtill, fared alwaye delicately, aparelled euer coſtly, ſtil open harted to their owne delights, but very narrowly cheſted to al others: which would haue ben reſonably ſatiſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt part of their ſuperfluous
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8971:5"/> prouiſion. Oh, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtates of our dayes would looke to this. Thoſe Lords; theſe knightes, and you the rich of this age, you ſuppoſe it your chiefe happines, to ioyne houſe to houſe, and lande to land, bloude to bloud, and thouſands to thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and yet yee hunger after more. But (alas) the moſt of theſe doe ſuppoſe it, their bleſſednes, to haue a Rowlande for an Oliuer: To banquet and furfette with Bacchus, &amp; to diſporte and ſléepe with Venus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To haue ſtore of children, great wealth, ſound bodies, ſtately buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, and noble names of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſorte. But beholde, both reaſon in earth, and tormentes in hell, ſhall teach you in trueth, that this is rather follie, then true felicitie. For if this be true happines, to be frée from al ſorts of miſery, and to abounde in all ſacietie of good things, without appetite of farther or deſire of more: howe can you reiecte reaſon, which telleth you (O earthly happie) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you are yet in great miſery? For though in riches, yée ſurpaſſe Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in carnal venery, Sardanapalus, in delicate diſſhes, either the Epicure, or Bacchus; in conioyned poſſeſſions euen
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8971:5"/> Alexander the conqueror: yet your miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable mindes thinke, though we haue much, yet haue we not ynough. We are ſorie our throtes be no déeper, our bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies no greater, our nights no longer, &amp; our patrimonies no larger. For had you wonne the whole world, yet would you couet to haue another, and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly yée feare the deſerued fall of this you haue, which is euermore enuironed with miſerable feare and blindnes, with feare to looſe that they haue, by ſundrie caſualties: And ſo blinde, as not able to beholde the miſerie of that ende, which hath none other heauen, then this preſent earth. But (Oh) come, and beholde the ſtate of theſe bleſſed that are not godly rich, (O yée ſonnes of men) and you ſhall bée enforced, if you hunger to bée truely bleſſed, to pray with that holy rich Dauid:<note place="margin">Pſal. 17.14.</note> 
               <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer my ſoule from the wicked with thy ſworde, from men (O Lorde) by thine hande, from men of the worlde, who haue their portion in this life, whoſe bellyes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thou filleſt with thine hidde treaſure: their children haue y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and leaue the reſt of their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8971:6"/> their ſubſtance for their children. But I will beholde thy face in righteouſneſſe, and when I awake, I ſhall bee ſatisfied with thine image.</hi> That is: When I ſhall ariſe from the ſleepe of naturall death, it ſhall bée full felicitie to me, that thou in thy mercy (O Lord) haſt made mee thy creature, and liuely image, formed by and after thée, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſſe and righteouſneſſe, and to enioy the fulneſſe of thy face,<note place="margin">Colloſſ. 2.</note> which is true bleſſedneſſe.</p>
            <p>The tormentes of Hell in Diues, might ſufficiently teach vs, howe falſe is the felicitie of earthly beautie, braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, dignitie, riches, and greateſt glorie: If Chriſt bée not in them, your ende ſhall bée wéeping and woe:<note place="margin">Iames.</note> Hée was braue, but now is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Godly Lazar beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull: he was of great poſſeſſions, but Lazarus hath the kingdome:<note place="margin">Luke. 16.</note> He gaped after gold, gay clothes, &amp; delicate fare, but the deſpiſed man of God, is truely rich, decked with glory &amp; delicately fed, with the countenance of the Lord. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues (ſuppoſed rich) is buried in hel. And by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he greatly offended, in that, he is greatly puniſhed: For his tongue is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8971:6"/> tormented in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flame, he cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for fauour, but cannot obtain: for hée had no part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (which is true beatitude:) and therefore muſt he néedes dwell for euer, in the ſeconde death. He would haue his brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that they dreame not of falſe felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but the very way to bleſſedneſſes, is there taught him (and alſo vs) not to bée learned from the deade:<note place="margin">Luke. 16.</note> but of the liuing Lawe of the Lord. <hi>They haue Moſes &amp; the Prophets, let them heare them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſai 8.19.20</note> Be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide ye gallants of the earth, you deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Nymphes of theſe deayes (which term it now moſt delicate to you) iudge your ſelues, that ye be not iudged of the Lorde.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> Burie not your mindes in fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned felicitie: but ſéeke you after true happineſſe. If riches, honours, Caſtels, Lordſhips, Lands, Reuenues, &amp; wordly goods greatly increaſe: ſet not your hearts vpon them. Be not locked into the Coffer of thy gold with Diues, but haue a godly liberal hart with Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Rather ſit at the doore of thy houſe ready to benefite thy countrie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, to runne from al thy homeſtedes, to lye aloofe to féede thy ſelfe. Haue a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8971:7"/> eye, to the whéele of falſe felicitie: For the more ſwéete ſhée ſéemeth, the ſharper is her looſe; &amp; whom ſhe moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth, him maketh ſhe moſt fottiſh. Truely the proſperitie of fooles deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them.<note place="margin">Prou. 1.32.</note> But if by grace from God, in thy part of the firſt reſurrection, thou withſtandeſt her pleaſures, and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſires:<note place="margin">Sizach.</note> thou crowneſt then thy life with felicitie in him: Which God grant vs for his holy Chriſts ſake. And thus much of falſe flattering felicite. But y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may be partakers of this bleſſednes, approued to vs here, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of god, let vs lend our hearts to heare. Truely this felicitie is firſt by the Lorde, diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to vs, in this life, but poſſeſſed by vs more amplie in heauen, at the houre of death, yet neuer fully obtained, till the time héere mentioned for the iuſt: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, at the ſecond reſurrection: When we ſhalbe fréed from all woe, and ſhalbe fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with all fulneſſe of ioy, and bée the prieſtes of God and Chriſt, to raigne with him a thouſand yeare: that is, for euer and euer.</p>
            <q>Bleſſed is he that hath part in the firſt reſurrection: for on ſuch, &amp;c.</q>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:8971:7"/>
            <p>This text doth firſt then yeld a reſolute anſwere to this demand, &amp; who are they which be truly bleſſed? Truely ſaith our text: euen whatſoeuer he, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath part in the firſt reſurrection, whether he be king or caytiffe, prince or potentate, preacher or people, rich or poore, he or ſhe, yong or old, one or other. Come vp hither ye ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, raiſe vp you your heauy harts: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catholik curſe of Adams loines, behold an vniuerſal beatitude, in our common Chriſt. This abſolute happineſſe is not ſhut vp to a few, but as many, as can be partakers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo many (I ſay) ſhal be bleſſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond death, which is the infernall lake of fire &amp; brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone. But for your better helpe to the comfort of this place, note héere w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mée, two thinges. The firſt: what is this firſt reſurrection. The ſeconde, how we may aſſure our ſelues to be partakers therof Now we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, our text doth inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate vnto vs a duple reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, a corporal &amp; a ſpiritual.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.2.20.</note> The corporal reſurrection, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupplie of this article: I beleeue the reſurrection of the deade, and is common to all: for all fleſhe ſhall die and ryſe agayne to iudgemente.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8971:8"/> But the ſpirituall reſurrection, is parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular to the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of God alone, &amp; is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the firſt, becauſe in this life, his holy ſpirit doeth kill the members of ſinne, to death in vs, &amp; rayſeth vs vp togither in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Epheſi. 2.</note> to a newneſſe of life. But ſo neceſſarie a doctrine it is, to bée dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vs of either reſurrection: that I may not omit, but ſpeake of them both. And, as many ſcriptures doe teſtifie the firſt: ſo it is my purpoſe to charge your memories but with one: but that ſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as may alone ſuffice our purpoſe at this time, and your vnderſtanding of Gods good pleaſure, in that iudgement. <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 20.11.12.13.14.15</note> 
               <hi>And I ſawe a great white throne, and one that ſate on it, from whoſe face fled away both the earth and heauen, and their place was no more founde. And I ſawe the dead both great and ſmall, ſtand before God, &amp; the books were opened, and an other booke was opened, which is the booke of life, and the deade were iudged of thoſe things, which were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the books according to their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. And the ſea gaue vp her dead which were in her, and death and hell deliuered vp the deade which were in them: and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8971:8"/> they were iudged euery man according to their workes. And death and hel were caſt into the lake of fire: this is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde death. And whoſoeuer was not founde in the booke of life written, was caſt into the lake of fire.</hi> This holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (beloued) doth moſt playnely lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, the order and maner of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, at the laſt day. And firſt the maieſtie of the iudge in his comming is deſcribed: Secondly, the maner of the iudgement, who they be, and wherof the Apparants be iudged. The Lords comming is with great glory, he ſitteth on a mightie ſeat, farre paſſing the iudicial thrones of the greateſt princes. And of neceſſitie that muſt bée a greate Seate,<note place="margin">Titus. 2.13. Luk. 1.32.</note> which muſt beare the God of might: It is a bright ſhining ſeate, all glorious, not with cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible golde or precious ſtone, but with the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly gleames, more bright then the Sunne beames, euen lightned with the brightneſſe of his diuine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as Chriſt hath ſaide:<note place="margin">Matt. 25.31.</note> 
               <hi>The ſonne of Man ſhal come in his glorie, and he ſhall ſit vppon the ſeate of his glorie, and all the holy Angels ſhall come with him.</hi> Whoſe glorious throne, doth euen teach
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8971:9"/> vs, that the Lords iudgements are pure and without ſpotte. No pleading at the barre, no bribing of the iudge, no fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by aqueſt, no fauour found for ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, nor loue or hate ſhall beare a ſway, but equitie alone in him ſhall then bee ſéene. Alſo his brightneſſe in comming, ſhal perce into the hearts and actes of al men, to manifeſt and lay open y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hidden ſecrets of the conſcience, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſentence of Paul:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>Iudge nothing before the time, vntill the Lord come, who wil lighten things that are hide in darkenes, &amp; make the councels of the hearts mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and then ſhal euery man haue praiſe of God. viz.</hi> as his labour aſketh. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the ſhinning ſunne and moone, the glittering ſtarres, yea, heauen &amp; earth ſhall be darkened, &amp; faile of their bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, before him. For like as the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſunne ſhinning, cauſeth the blaſing torch to looſe his brightnes, in reſpect of him: So ſhall that moſt beawtifull pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, be as darkened with the great glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of this ſhining throne, in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Amightie Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But (my beloued) if theſe glorious creatures ſhal flée from the preſence of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8971:9"/> this mighty CHRIST, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to iudgement, which euer haue béene obedient to his holy will; yea, &amp; that but when he is comming: how ſhal it fare with vs, when he is ſet vpon that terrible throne whoſe ſinnes haue béene ſo many, and the accuſers ſo ready, (as the Lord his witnes, ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s accuſation,<note place="margin">Zopho.</note> and thine owne conſcience, which is to thée 1000. witneſſes) when the ſunne is blacke, the Moone as blood, the ſtars fall,<note place="margin">Malach.</note> like the gréene figges from their trées, in a mightie wind, the heauens depart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way like a ſcroll,<note place="margin">Reue. 6.12.</note> and all yſles and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, are moued out of their places. And the kinges the of earth, &amp; the great men, and the rich men, &amp; the chiefe cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and the mightie men, and euery bondman and euery frée man, hide them ſelues in dennes,<note place="margin">Eſa. 2.19. Hoſ. 10.8. Luk 23.30.</note> and amongſt the rocks of the mountaines, and ſhall ſay to the mountaines and rockes, fall on vs, and hide vs from the preſence of him, that ſitteth on the throne, and from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrath of the lambe. In cauſe hereof, let me ſay vnto vs, with that holy Dauid; Oh,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.22.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this, you that forget God, leaſt the Lorde teare you in péeces, and there bée
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8971:10"/> none to deliuer you. Séeing therefore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all theſe thinges muſt be diſſolued (and come to paſſe) what manner of perſons ought we to bée,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.11.</note> in holy conuerſation &amp; godlineſſe? But when this iudge our Lorde Chriſt is thus gloriouſlyſet, then theſe foreſaid perſons of ech degrée, ſhall ſtand before him, euen great &amp; ſmal: for neither heauen nor earth can hid them, or their crownes, their dignities, Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips or warrelike courage, wealth, wil, or wit, ſhall be able to kéepe them from his preſence, or eſcape the iuſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which the balance of his equitie ſhal caſt vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Looke to this now, ye knights and gentils here preſent, and you rich in poſſeſſions, be not careles of your life: for godly preuention nowe, ſhal embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den your perſons then, to lift vp your heades, becauſe your redemption is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at hand.<note place="margin">Luk. 21.28.</note> This order then ſhall be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: The bookes ſhal be laid open before the Lorde: and euery man high and low, rich and poore, ſhall be iudged with the ſcepter of trueth, euen according as his déedes are written in thoſe bookes. Note héere (beloued) by an elegant Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor, howe the ſpirite of GOD doth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8971:10"/> diſplay the iudgementes of the Lorde. He alludeth vnto the iudiciall courtes of kinges and Potentates, where the bookes of recorde beare memorie of the faultes of men conuicted by good proofe. Not that the Lord hath néede of bookes: for he knoweth the thoughts, words and workes of all men, &amp; of euery idle word,<note place="margin">Math. 12.36.</note> ſhall man be iudged: but, that héereby, he would ſende vs, to our owne ſenſes, to knowe and féele, that all our actions and heartes are in his ſight, and cannot be wiped out of his remembrance by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther penſill, then onely by true faith &amp; repentance. And as we are fallen into this Metaphor, of the Lords bookes: So let vs know that the holy ſcriptures,<note place="margin">Ezech. 18. Heb. 6.</note> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute thrée bookes vnto God: <hi>viz. liber prouidentiae, Iudicii, &amp; vitae:</hi> The booke of his prouidence: The booke of his iudgement: and the bleſſed booke of life. Of his prouidence, Dauid ſaith thus:<note place="margin">Pſal. 139 16.</note> 
               <hi>Thine eyes did ſee mee, when I was without fourme: for in thy booke were all things writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which in continuaunce were faſhioned, when there was none of them before. O Lorde</hi> (ſayth hée)
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8971:11"/> 
               <hi>when as yet I was not formed in my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe, thine eyes did ſee me, &amp; in the book of thy foreknowledge &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of thy diuine mind, were all men written from the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation of the earth, when as yet there was not one begotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The booke of his iudgementes, this former text doth enforce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſideration of, which bookes were opened, and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth the certaine knowledge, of al the words and workes, of euery man, from Adam, tyll that inſtant, according to the which, they ſhall be all then iudged. For thoſe things, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord now know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, as if he had them written in bookes, thoſe thinges, that either our heartes, wordes or workes, haue imagined, ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or done, the ſame then ſhall he then lay before vs, as if he redde them out of them,<note place="margin">Apoc. 20.</note> and ſhall thereby builde a reaſon vnto vs all, why ſome ſhall by iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment goe to hell, ſome other vnto life. Be not deceiued therefore (good people) God is not mocked or beguiled:<note place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> for we ſhall be adiudged of euery idle worde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall be ſpoken: howe much more, of wicked déeds: as of idolatrie, whordome, blaſphemie and ſuch like? Nowe go too,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8971:11"/> you that put farre away the euill day,<note place="margin">Amos. 6.3.</note> and approch the ſeat of iniquitie, which take ſingular pleaſure in ribauldry and filthy ieſting: which can laughe the lowdeſt, when your lewde ſeruants are moſt diſpoſed to lie. Doe you thinke indéed, ther is a God, that knoweth this? A Scribe, that recordeth it? A iudge, that will reuenge it? and a day, that ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale it, by the bookes of your heauie iudgement? And dare you continue your delight, in lying, whoring, in filthy ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinges, that are not comely, in ſuch the workes of darkeneſſe, which rather you ought to reprooue in others, then to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour or practiſe them your ſelues? But theſe euils dwel not altogether in beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, but you, you, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you: (I ſay) who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord hath bleſſed with landes and reuenewes in great aboundance, which for your birthes, are called gentlemen, &amp; for your chiualrie, knights: but for your follie, flattered as fooles, to winne of you preferment: euen of you (I ſaid) there are, that dare diſpiſe the ſpirit of trueth, with the falſe ſpirit of lying, ribauldry, and filthy whoredome. Your ſeruantes perceyuing your fooliſhneſſe, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8971:12"/> to ſell themſelues to hel, to gaine ſome earthly preferment at your han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. For, ſéeing your diuelliſh diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they frame their practiſe to your pleaſurs: but you ſhalbe iudged of thoſe thinges moſt ſeuerely. Oh, you ſeruing-men abſteyne from pleaſing your mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, with this egregious lewdenes of lying. Wotte you what you doe? and whoſe ye are?<note place="margin">Io. 8.</note> you do make your ſoules the ſlaues of ſathan, and you are herein, the children of the deuill your father, which is a lyer from the beginning. Caſt of theſe works of darkeneſſe, haue no fellowſhip with them, but rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue them, and thoſe that vſe them, yea, though they be your great maſters. For, you are not called to ſerue men, but God. And you ſhall then be founde beſt profitable to your maiſters, when you ſhall take ſinne from their bodies, and exhort vertue to their ſoules. And be it knowne to you, you knightes héere pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and the reſt, that, that noble <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aman</hi> had not béene clenſed from his le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, had he not humbled his ſoule to the admonition of his godly ſeruing-men. <hi>2. Kings. 5.13.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 5.13</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:8971:12"/>
            <p>The Lorde GOD worke our conuerſion in tyme, that wee may dye to ſinne, and haue parte in the firſte reſurrection: ſo ſhall we bee ſure not to taſte of the ſeconde death: becauſe our names are founde written, in the booke of life: Whereof nowe wee are to ſpeake. And it is notable, that it is ſaide, euery man was iudged ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to his workes, that hée had done in his life time, not what others haue done for him, after. Yea, aſwell the godly as the reprobate, are in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues vnder the cenſure of the ſeconde booke, that is, condemnable to the ſeconde death.</p>
            <p>But now there is an other cauſe, why the godly are ſaued: namely, that their names are written in the booke of life.<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.2.</note> This booke of life is not of this life cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, but ſpiritual, and hath his begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in theſe our dayes, but is perfited in the laſt reſurrection, and is called the moſt ſure, and ſwéete election and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination of god, which doth ſeale and ſanctifie to himſelfe, thoſe that be his, whom he hath choſen to be partakers of the firſt reſurrection, before the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8971:13"/> of dayes:<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.2.</note> and therefore they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not periſhe in the ende of time. Of this booke ſpeaketh Paule: <hi>The Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth who bee his.</hi> And though ſparingly I would ſpeak in ſingular reuerence of this hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myſtery,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.19.</note> to many in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, &amp; comfortable only to the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of life, when their eyes be opened to reade this booke: yet in humbleneſſe of heart, I ſay thus much of it: This booke of life, is the moſt certaine, ſure, firme, and eternall foreknowledge in the moſt holy minde of God,<note place="margin">Zanch. To. 2 lib. 3. cap. 3. 712.</note> by the which hee euer hath and doeth in his Chriſt, and for him alone, appoint and chooſe vs, to be his children adopted to grace, and heires of eternall life, approueth them for his, and taketh peculiar and perpetuall care on them. <hi>I knowe my ſheepe, ſaith Chriſt: I knowe whome I haue chooſen &amp;c.</hi> And thoſe whome the Lorde writeth in this booke, thoſe only ſhall haue ſaith and life. And whoſoeuer is not written in this booke, without doubt, he ſhall be caſt into the ſeconde death. But howe ſhal we know that wee are written in this booke? Surely euerie man is to ſéeke the knowledge héereof. To ſome it is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8971:13"/> giuen at morne, to other at noone, and to ſome onely at night, euen gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping at breath. The ordinarie way to this knowledge is elega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſet downe by Paul to the Romans, where the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God are ſo linked in one, &amp; ſo eaſie to be perceiued, that euerie man may haue an inſight, of this golden cheine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> feareth God.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> 
               <hi>We know that all thinges (ſaith he) worke together for the beſt, to to them that loue God, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them that are called of his purpoſe. For thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he knew before, he alſo predeſtinate to be made like to the image of his ſonne, that he might be the firſt borne amonge manie brethren.</hi> Moreouer, <hi>Whome he predeſtinate, them alſo hee called, and whome hee called, them alſo hee iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and whome he iuſtified, them alſo he glorified.</hi> Héere, beloued, the booke is gods purpoſe to chooſe, and our wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in it is, that we are elected to liue in Chriſt before all times, a life confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to the following of Chriſt: to bée holy and blameles, ſober &amp; godly, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; iuſt, peaceable and bleſſed in this preſent worlde: And not to be worldly bent, and to blaſpheme with rebellious
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8971:14"/> ſpirites, ſaying: what ſhould I feare to to robbe, to kil, to ſpoile, to whore it, and brace it, and to followe my luſt? For, if I be elected, I ſhalbe ſaued: if I be not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, I ſhalbe da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned. But beloued, Oh, hateful ſpirit againſt Gods holy ſpirit of our electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Do you draw hence an other nature in the grace of this book? namely, learne to ſée, how thoſe that are elected, thoſe ſhalbe called to féele their election. And they ſhalbe iuſtified from their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer corruptions, ſanctified from after ſinnes: and glorified to God. But as we haue ſaid, thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be not found writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this booke, thoſe ſhalbe iudged by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other bookes of iudgement, and that according to their workes. This doctrine is héere deliuered vs to note: Iohn ſpeaketh of the generall iudgement, executed long after the natural death, and he ſpeaketh generally of all, when as (no doubte) great heapes of infinite thouſands, haue had the works of Popes and Cardinals, popiſh prieſts, and ſacrilegious Maſſes, trentals, doles and chauntrie fées, moon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh builde and frieriſh helpes for them. All whoſe works of darkneſſe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, euery man ſhall riſe vnchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8971:14"/> from his former ſtate: For, euen ſo as he dyed, ſuch ſhall he ariſe, and ſhall haue iudgement after his owne works, and not according to the merite of other mens labours for him after his death. Thus ſaith Gods ſpirite, which cannot lye: Away therefore with your prayer for the deade, your almes and dole to the poore, at the place and day of Funerals. And euen this day I exhort in the Lord, whom it doth moſt concerne, that as I knowe, and doe affirme your hate, to that peſtilent péece of popery, and your ſinceritie in Chriſt: ſo yée faithfully ſhewe it at this inſtant. Féede theſe poore aſſembled, but foſter not that popiſhe opinion, to pray for the ſoule departed. Forget not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord at this preſent, who hath not forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bring you to great things. Abſtain (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle) not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from euill: but euen alſo from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow &amp; ſhew of euill. If it might be, take ſome other day for them &amp; giue them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> warning, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you meane no procuring of prayer for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead. For I know, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you are aſſured, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery man ſhall appeare and aunſwere for his owne factes, as well this reuerend corps going to his graue,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8971:15"/> as all you and wee here aſſembled, in cauſe of him. <hi>We muſt all appeare (ſaith Paule) before the iudgement ſeate of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>that euery man may receiue the things that are done in his bodie, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that he hath done, whether it be good or euill.</hi> The Lord in mercy bleſſe vs with his grace, that liuing in him, we may die in the Lorde Chriſt, and ſo reſt in peace, till our returne to this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily reſurrection, when we ſhall reſigne to our ſoules, our newe bodies, though burned to aſhes, eaten with vermine, in Sea, or by lande: For death, lande and ſea, ſhall giue vppe, not newe creatures, but her receiued deade, to be revnited, to this reſurrection. And ſo with holy Iob, we ſhall all ſée our redéemer, not with other, but with theſe eyes, that nowe we haue, and with the ſelfe ſame bodies which nowe we beare, ſhall wée all both ſmall and great, ſtande before the almightie Chriſt, the iudge of quick and deade. To whom be glory for euer. And nowe time requireth to ſpeake of the firſt reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which earſt we cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſpirituall. And of this reſurrection Paul ſpeaketh thus:<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>And when we were
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8971:15"/> deade by ſinnes, God in his rich mercie, through his great loue, wherewith hee loued vs, hath quickened vs together in Chriſt, by whoſe grace wee are ſaued: And hath raiſed vs vp together, &amp; made vs ſit together in the heauenly places in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.4</note> And againe to the Romans thus: <hi>We are buried then with Chriſt by baptiſme, into his death, that like as Chriſt was raiſed of God the father, ſo wee ſhoulde walke in newneſſe of life.</hi> And nowe of theſe places we are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue: Firſt, that there is a death, that goeth before this reſurrection. Then, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by an other power, beyonde our ſelues, we are reuiued, and raiſed from that death. And thirdly, what this life is, where vnto we are raiſed. To the firſt, this death is ſpiritual, and is none other but ſinne, as here is ſaide: and when we were deade in ſinne. And rightly is ſin called death: for it killeth all the vitall partes of the ſoule, and maketh it not onely vnapt, but vnable to ſerue the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God. It depriueth vs of the grace of God. It ſeparateth Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> which is our life, from vs, it bringeth ſathan to poſſeſſe our ſoules, and haleth vs to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8971:16"/> ſecond death: which is the infernal lake. This is the nature of euery ſinne, and therefore they are rightly ſaide to bée deade, which be poſſeſſed of it: as whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cut off from God, eſtraunged from his life,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.6.</note> and deade to godlyneſſe. So are the laſhing widowes called deade in ſpirite, though they liue by nature, which giue themſelues to carnalitie &amp; fleſhly luſts. And of ſuch men alſo ſpake Chriſt the Lorde, ſaying: <hi>Let the deade burie their dead.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 8.22</note> Nowe (beloued) drawe hence this doctrine: We are by courſe of naturall life ſinners, but by our ſelfe delights, we are become deade in treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes: but he that is dead, is ſo frée from life, that he hath no part of whatſoeuer is done vnder the ſunne: as the preacher ſaith.<note place="margin">Eccle. 9.4.5.6.</note> So now that I ſpeake to you, that you conceiue, and we all féele the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the voyce, it is by that wee liue: but this Corpes héere preſent, is ſo frée from all this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he neither heareth, or conceiueth, féeleth, or partaketh, whatſoeuer by his occaſion héere is done: for hée is deade, and his life is not in him: Euen ſo (beloued) the deade in ſinne are as frée from righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8971:16"/> and the true féeling thereof: as this ſanctified corpes is cut from our preſent action. Moreouer this corps can neither goe, nor ſtir, hinder or let thoſe, that liſt to carry &amp; conuey him whether they woulde: Neither can the deade in ſinne, withſtande the guide of his dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoule, the killing diuell the prince of hell, but is ledde and drawen, euen whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and to what him luſt: to whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, murthers, lying, blaſphemie, and what not?<note place="margin">Ion. 8.34. Rom. 6.20. 2. Pet. 2.19.</note> For of whom ſo euer a man is ouercome, his ſeruant he is, whether of ſinne vnto death, or of grace vnto life. Laſt of all, it is not in the power of any deade man to ariſe againe, till his life be returned to him: No more is it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of man once deade in ſin, to riſe againe from it: vntill his life, which is Chriſt, returne, to reuiue him. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle ſaith, hee hath quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs, euen God the father, by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of his Chriſt, hath raiſed vs vp with Chriſt. Where is then thy frée will, and power, to kéepe the wayes of God? when thou haſt eares, but fatted eares, that cannot heare: a heart, but blinded,<note place="margin">Matt. 13.14.</note> that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not perceiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good wil of god: a ſoule,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8971:17"/> but deade and eſtraunged from the life of God.<note place="margin">Ephe. 41.8.</note> And for this cauſe God is ſaide, to raiſe vs from the deade, that Chriſt may giue vs light, &amp; that by his mighty operation through faith in him. It is his mighty operation,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.12.</note> not mans weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to raiſe vs from ſinne: For ſathan is ſtronger then we,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.26.</note> &amp; holdeth vs (once dead) eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at his wil, as Paul ſaith, ſo as it is not poſſible for vs, to ariſe from his bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>os, til our life Chriſt, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.29. Math. 12.29. Mark. 3.22.</note> enter combat with him, bind him, &amp; take vs (his ſpoile) away from him. The workeman then to raiſe vs in this firſt reſurrection, is not man, but God. And he vſeth heereto (as his finger to forme vs anewe) his worde and his ſpirite, &amp; both from him ſelfe: that he might haue the whole glorie of our life. Embrace then this holy meanes, come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word, there is his ſpirit. If thou be his he will drawe thée to it, lighten thée by them, &amp; raiſe thée from this ſpirituall death, as the Apoſtle hath ſaide,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>If the ſpirite of him that raiſed vp Ieſus from the deade dwell in you, hee that raiſed vp Chriſt from the deade, ſhall alſo quicken your mortall bodies, becauſe that his ſpirite
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8971:17"/> dwelleth in you.</hi> Nowe what this reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is, the Apoſtle doth tel vs: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, newneſſe of life, ſaying:<note place="margin">Rom. 6.4</note> 
               <hi>We are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried then with Chriſt by baptiſme into his death, that like as Chriſt was raiſed from the dead by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorie of the father: ſo wee ſhould walke in newneſſe of life.</hi> This is then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt reſurrection: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, newnes of life. There muſt be life (beloued) as well in the ſpirite as in the bodie. Manie men ſéeme to liue, and to doe the works of life, but not in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, but in the body: to ſerue their turn, to anſwere the law, to obſerue the time, but all this while the ſpirite liueth not. Many a papiſt to day will come to Church in bodie, but he bringeth a deade ſoule with him: for Chriſtian Religion hath no roume in his heart. But if thou wilt haue thy part (Papiſt or Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant) in the firſt reſurrection, thou muſt beginne to liue in thy ſpirite, that thy ſpirite may enforce thy bodie, to loue, liue, and feare thy God. According to this ſentence of Paule:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.22.</note> 
               <hi>Caſt off the olde man, which is corrupt through the deceiueable luſtes, and bee yee renewed in the ſpirite of your minde, and put
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8971:18"/> on the newe man, which after God is created in righteouſneſſe and true holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> And at one worde to ſpeake it, herein conſiſteth the firſt reſurrection: To caſt away the works of darkeneſſe, and to put on, Chriſt the armour of light. But, as no man raiſed from a fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy puddle, will willingly beare with him the myerie ſpots of that dirtie ſoile, but will rather caſt away the defyled garments that he might appeare clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed:<note place="margin">Hoſ. 3.</note> Euen ſo (beloued) wee muſt not part ſtakes with God and ſinne, but we muſt ſay to ſinne, get thée hence by a ſpirituall hatred vnto her, &amp; ſo increaſe in it, that we muſt (as the Apoſtle Iude ſaith) euen hate the very garment that is polluted by the fleſhe.<note place="margin">verſ. 23.</note> So muſt we (hauing receiued ſuch grace) liue in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and bodie, as the ſonnes of lighte, tranſlated from the power of death, to the kingdome of Chriſt in all peace,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.13.</note> Godlynes,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.11.</note> ſobrietie and honeſtie. Thus ſhal we liue, &amp; raigne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeare, viz. for euer. Now call your ſpirites to your ſenſes, and ſée howe yée ſauour this trueth, (beloued in Chriſt) Rowſe vppe your drowſie heartes and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8971:18"/> with the perſpicuitie of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſifte and ſearch your ſelues euerie one, howe you haue profited by this doctrine, and whether you liue or die. Be not deceiued, God is not mocked: whatſoeuer a man ſoweth, that ſhall hée reape. For, if yée ſowe ſtill to the fleſh, your former corruptions, you ſhal reape the ſeconde death. But if nowe, you can take hold of Chriſts doctrin, by his ſpirit, &amp; from his truth ſowe to your ſpirits, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſéeds of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of Faith, of righteouſnes of peace, and godlyneſſe,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> you are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers then of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt reſurrection; and ſhal reape hereof, life euerlaſting. And in this examination, two ſorts of men, are meruellouſly conuinced. The firſt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther féeling death or life in god, runneth headlong to his luſte, in infidelitie and gréedineſſe to ſinne: as though that onely were his chiefe beatitude. And theſe bée the Atheiſtes of our dayes, whoſe conſciences are ſeared vppe with an hotte yron, ſo, as no worde can pearce into their heartes, or ſappe of Gods ſpirite haue courſe in their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, but are paſt all féeling, euen at the point of damnation.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:8971:19"/>
            <p>The ſeconde ſort, are of ſuch, as hauing ſome ſparkes, of a former fire, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle breathing force of an elder ſtrength, (but nowe decaying) doe yet ſéeme to liue: when rather it may be feared, that they are almoſt deade. And theſe are notably ſhadowed vnto vs by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of Sardi in the Apocalips.<note place="margin">Apoca. 3.1.</note> And writte vnto the Angel (.i. the Miniſter) of the Church which is at Sardi: <hi>Theſe things ſaith he, that hath the ſeuen ſpirites of God in his hand, and the 7. ſtars, I knowe thy workes: for thou haſt a name that thou liueſt, but thou art deade.</hi> Oh (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) marke well this Church of Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di or Lidia. She is not an idolatrous Church, but profeſſing God and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. She hath the forme of Gods go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, his worde, his miniſters, &amp; is called his Church. She ſéemeth for her outward ſhew, to be moſt Chriſtian and holy: but in déede and troth, ſhee is conuicted of death. And that not becauſe ſhée hath no part of godly life in her, but becauſe ſhe hath fallen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her firſt loue, life, and ſtrength in him, that holdeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manifold graces (called <hi>7,</hi> ſpirits) in his hande, to diſpoſe at his good pleaſure, &amp;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8971:19"/> the ſufficient number of his preachers, named ſtarres, to ſhine into the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mans nature, with the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his word. Finally, Sardi is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe is imperfect in her workes before God: that is, ſhe was but an hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall Church, reſted in the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ceremonies and rites, but ſought not the Lorde, in trueth and ſinceritie. And héere note, beloued, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Church, or people, which hath not in her ſoule, the rooted faith of Chriſt, graft by his ſpirite, in that inner Man, in ſtrength wherof, the force and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Chriſts ſpirite floweth thence, into an open practiſe of holineſſe and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, righteouſneſſe and honeſtie: That ſame Church, people, or ſeuered perſon is as deade before the Lord. But yet in this Church of Lidia, there were a fewe names, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord noteth in the 4. ver. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>3.</hi> chap. which had not defiled their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, had not ſtained y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> profeſſion of Chriſt, which Chriſt, they by baptiſm, had put on &amp; is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wedding garment, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orning our beauty in him, &amp; couereth our infirmities &amp; iniquities, from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of gods iuſtice. Very comfortable is
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8971:20"/> this to the Godly, but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked moſt terrible. The Lordes eyes beholde the hearts and actes of men, and doth daily diſcerne the number of the Godly: but kéepeth recordes of the wickeds practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes, againſt the day of wrath. O Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, Englande, Oh thou Church of Sardi, if thou be looked into with a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall eye, thou ſhalt be founde néere vnto death: onely a fewe names or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are kept in thée, for a reſerued ſéed to the Lorde. In outwarde ſhew, what Church more holy? Thy Princes are proteſtants: Thy angelical ſtarres, thy biſhops and preachers, are learned tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers; Thy gouernement is godly, thy profeſſion is holy: But (O Englande) if thou be ſounded to the heart, thou ſhalt be founde (I feare me) verie ſicke and néere vnto death. Many maladies haue mette with thée, no ſickeneſſe, but hath taken holde of thée, and ſore weakened thy ſtrength: But laſt of al, hypocriſie &amp; ſecuritie ſléepe in thy boſome. Thou ſtaineſt thy bright veſture of holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion with the filthy ſpottes of carnall deſires: Thy religion, is a cloake to all thy iniquities. But as a ſpot is ſoone e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpied,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8971:20"/> and ſéemeth moſt foule in a ſcarlet robe: So the brighter thy profeſſion is, the ſooner thy ſinnes are diſcouered, and thine imperfections more notorious. But by two eſpeciall notes, a ſicke man is knowne to be neare his death. Firſt, his pulſes labour weakely, his ſpeech draweth farrely, and his ſtrength is fled away: Secondly when he is ſodeinely bereft of his vitall ſpirits &amp; perfect ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſo as he is not féeling y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parts of his dying bodie, he is déemed neare vnto his death. Alas, looke into the bodie of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, for the ſoundenes of her life, Chriſt in her; &amp; beholde, her pulſes beate faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, her ſpeach fetcheth farly, her ſtrength is meruellouſly decayed. Is her zeale to religion, as it was in the beginning of her maieſties raigne? Is it continually vigent in all the parts of the bodie? doth euery knée bowe to Chriſt the Lorde in her? doth euery tongue confeſſe Ieſus to be the Lorde, to the glorie of God the father? Nay, (alas) this little life left, is drawne néere to the heart, and the heart is verie ſicke. A fewe names, a fewe, in reſpecte of ſo great a number. What meaneth it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo many magiſtrates are
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8971:21"/> moleſted with carcke againſt conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and domeſticall furies? That ſuch and ſo great vices, are dayly ſpread, and breake out? So ſundrie perſons forced, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> papiſts filthy familyes and popiſh ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries? Such friendſhippe to Gods enimies of ſome, that rather ſhould help to ſpewe them out of the bodie? Such prouiſion for warre? ſuch feare of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine foes? and ſo ſmall truſt in manie home dwellers? vndoubtedly, this is the very cauſe, that Englande is very ſicke, fainting &amp; falling, as by degrées, from her former ſtrength in Chriſt. Religion is thought to bee ſtrong ynough of it ſelfe: for aide it can obtaine little, except about the heart. Godly conuerſation is fledde out of the countrie, God graunt him godly, &amp; conſtant entertainment in her graces Court. Charity is become key cold: for no man hath leaſure to loue beyonde himſelfe. Hate of iniquitie is baniſhed the lande, and the true loue of God is hardly to be founde, in the bodie of England. Euen now is performed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the prophet Hoſias ſpeach: <hi>There is no truth nor mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſe. 4 2.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>nor knowledge of God in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land: by ſwearing, &amp; lying, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8971:21"/> killing, and ſtealing, and whoring, they breake out, and bloode toucheth blood: therefore ſhall the lande mourne &amp;c.</hi> And are we not ſenſeleſſe of our weake eſtate? Do not our ſpirituall preachers crie vnto vs?<note place="margin">Eſa. 1.53.6. Rom. 2.2.</note> There is no health fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> top to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> toe. All haue gone aſtray, euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after his picked &amp; choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> way: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of God, hath béene to drawe you to repentance, but you haue abuſed his great pacience, &amp; are like to the raging ſeas: for in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of your preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, you haue caſt vp to the eyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, the filthie fome of your bloodgiltineſſe. But nowe repent in time, ere the day of his decrée come foorth.<note place="margin">Zoph. 2.1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Gather your ſelues together (O nation not worthy to bée beloued) leaſt you be blowen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way like chaffe, in that day. Séeke the Lorde ye méeke of the earth, you that haue wrought his iudgementes. Séeke righteouſneſſe, ſéeke lowlines, if ſo be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye may bée hidden in the day of the lords wrath. But, beloued in GOD,<note place="margin">Eſa. 26.20.</note> howe féele we our ſelues now? are we ſicke or whole? To this me thinke ſome do ſay: No, ſir: <hi>loquere no bis placentia,</hi> ſpeake more pleaſant things to vs. Crie, peace,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8971:22"/> peace,<note place="margin">Iere. 20.1.</note> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> til y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of war. Caſt Ieremie into priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaith Paſhur, &amp; his partakers: for hee ſpeaketh againſt this citie. But thoſe names onely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are about the hart, and haue not ſo ſteined their cloths, they ſay: he is not worthie to die: for he hath ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord our god.<note place="margin">Ier. 26.16.</note> But of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſidue, what ſhal we ſay? tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we may rightly ſay as God him ſelfe ſpake to his prophet Ezechiel, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time, ſaying: <hi>Alſo thou ſon of man, the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy people, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> talke of thee by the wals (as they ſit at their banquets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezec. 33.30.</note> 
               <hi>y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art their ſauce to their delicates) &amp; in the dores of their houſes, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſit in the ſtreets to recreate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; ſpeake one to an other, ſaying: (in deriſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my law) come I pray you, &amp; heare what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the Lorde: for they come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, as the people vſeth to come, and my people ſit before thee, and heare thy words, but they wil not do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for with their mouths they make (mowes &amp;) ieſtes &amp; their hart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> goeth after their couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And lo, Thou art to them, as a ieſting ſong, of one that hath a pleaſant voice, &amp; can ſing well: for they heare thy words, but they do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not. And when this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8971:22"/> to pas (for lo, it wil come) (namely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ripenes of this ſin, &amp; the performance of my prophets threts fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me) Then ſhal they knowe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe. 28.</note> 
               <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (not a ieſting ſinger but) a prophet hath ben amongſt them. When Lord? euen whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I wil lay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land deſolate (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord) &amp; waſt, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pompe of her ſtrength ſhal ceaſe, &amp;c.</hi> O lord in thy great mercy looke down vpon our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Iſrael. What is he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſéeth this huge heape of people, here this day being a ſtraunger to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate of this country, but preſently might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue much life of god to be in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Surely it is a great people, yea a very great auditorie: I haue not ſeene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like in the countrie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord bleſſe you al, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the firſt reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, according to his bleſſed will. But you of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greater ſort, take you care, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye come not to heare what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord ſaith, only for ciuility or nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borly courteſie, in reſpect of theſe fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals: or in niſenes, to heare a voice that might delight you: but what cauſe ſoeuer brought you, now y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you are come: be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you may be taught of god. As for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greteſt number, it is too ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, &amp; wil be proued anonne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as our prophet ſaith, they folow their couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8971:23"/> They are come in hope to haue a dole to day. Againſt whoſe gréedie deſire eftſones I pray you, to whom it belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, that regarde may be had hereof: leaſt this dayes exerciſe, may be abuſed by the wicked, to father their popiſh prayer for the deade, vppon your cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable deuotion to the poore. But (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) let the bell call you to another Church, or at an other time, be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher liked neuer ſo well, &amp; we ſhall not haue the thirde part of this audience. Nay, if we might haue but the fourth part, and that on the Sabboth onely, it were in theſe partes a vertuous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And after our hearing, howe do we digeſt the worde? For the moſte part, this is al: At dinner, and after, we talke of the man, but féede not of the matter: We either yéelde him his due commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, or our diſlike: But euen as min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrels ſong once hearde, is ſtreight for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: So very fewe, with Marie, lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vp in his heart, thoſe things which the Prophet ſpake, Take héede that you ſpurne not at your Phiſicions: for then your health is at an ende. Did Eſay cry in his time,<note place="margin">Eſa. 53.1.</note> lord, who beléeueth our ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings?
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8971:23"/> And may not we cry nowe, Lord, who doeth credite our report? We are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ofſcowring of the people, the laughing-ſtockes of the worlde, wée are counted contentious, ſeditious, ſlaunderous, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, lyers, &amp; troublers, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate. But as for this people, (though thou O Lord) ſpeake in vs vnto them, yet will they not bend their eares, to heare thy voyce in vs. Though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth be wearie of her ſinnefull burthen, &amp; as ſurcharged (with the heauineſſe of ſinne) doth vniuerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly totter as a dronken man,<note place="margin">Aprill 8. 1580.</note> at our iniquities, and thy heauie iudgements: yea though the waters here below, the heauens &amp; planets farre aboue, though blaſing gleames, and burning lampes, haue ſummoned vs, and vgly ſhapes in monſtrous birth, haue and yet doe cite vs, to the preuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy heauie wrath in true repentaunce:<note place="margin">Iere. 8.6.</note> yet no man ſayth to himſelfe, and what haue I done? But euerie man goeth to the corruption of his owne heart, and fetcheth thence, the labor of his life, in Hypocriſie, Popery, Drunkenneſſe, Whoredome, couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, pride, ambition, atheiſme &amp; ſuch like. And all this commeth hereof, that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8971:24"/> being almoſt all dead, we féele not, that we are once touched with ſickenes. We goe on in our wickednes, and ſéeke cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit againſt our reprouers, &amp; ſcorne at Gods iudgementes, and when moſt ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming is of imminent daunger: wee aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure our ſelues of great ſecuritie. Oh people of this waywarde nation and you here preſent, let vs his miniſters bee the Lordes cockes, to rowſe you out of this deadely ſléepe, hauing firſt with Peters teares, examined well our ſelues. Let vs bee the trumpettes of the Lord, to warne you of the greate and mightie battel of the God of hoſtes againſt vs. And nowe accept you this labour of me, the watchman of the Lorde, and hearken with comfort to this my crye: <hi>Ariſe you that ſleepe in your ſinnes and ſhamefull ſecuritie (O Chriſtians by name) Ariſe from the firſt death of ſinne, by the operation of Gods holy ſpirite in you, and walke in newneſſe of life, by the light of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious goſpell of GOD, giuen you in Chriſt, ſo ſhal not the ſecond death haue any power of you: becauſe you haue taken parte in the firſt reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:8971:24"/>
            <p>And now I perceiue this firſt parte hath taken my whole time allotted me, ſo as I can not ſpeake of the ſeconde, which is ſo depending of the firſt, that well they can not bee diſioyned. But in aſmuch as your ciuill ſolemnities, aſke more tyme, then poſſibly the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone woulde afforde vs, I will deferre my ſeconde part till ſome other time, except I receiue your pleaſures, far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to procéede. Well then: knowing now your godly deſires, by the harald at armes, that I ſhoulde procéede: Let vs read our ſecond part, and it is thus:
<q>For on ſuch the ſecond death hath no power,<note place="margin">Text ver. 6.</note> but they ſhal be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſtes of god and Chriſt, and ſhall raigne with him a thouſand yeare.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In this part (dearely beloued) the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt doth by a moſt elegant phraſe, deſcribe the ſtate &amp; conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, affirming the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo farre of to be once touched, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> punct of natural death, with the paines of hell or falſe fained
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:8971:25"/> popiſh purgatorie, that contrarily, they preſently are in bliſſe with God, ſinging with the ſpirits of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſt, the due pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Lord: ſaying, <hi>for on ſuch. &amp;c.</hi> But to the further openyng of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent part, let vs obſerue theſe thrée thinges: Firſt what is to be vnderſtoode by this ſecond death. Secondly, of what prerogatiue &amp; power y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame is. And laſt of al, for a final concluſion, what, &amp; wher is the ful felicitie of the iuſt, which haue their part in the firſt reſurrection. The ſecond death, (to be ſhorte) is that which followeth the firſte, as a merite of his deſerte. But death is ſaid to be twofold, in the holy ſcriptures. For as there is a death of the body, ſo is there likewiſe a death of the ſoule. But of death of the bodie, we haue ſaide before: And of the naturall death, Gods holy booke, our common experience: and the dead body of this departed Chriſtian before vs, beareth perfecte teſtimony. Of which the Apoſtle Paule ſayth: It is decreed that man ſhall once die, and then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his iudgement. And our Apoſtle in this booke:<note place="margin">Heb. 9.27. Apoc. 14.13</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are the dead, which die in the Lord: (or for the Lords cauſe)
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8971:25"/> for they reſt from their labours, ſo ſaith the ſpirite, and their works follow them.</hi> Their owne workes followe them, not the workes of other for them. And be it knowne vnto you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the firſt death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule, (which is ſinne and iniquitie) is the verie cauſe procuring Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to ſtrike the bodie with naturall death, and is héere called the firſt death of the body. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which, the ſoule, that dieth in ſinne, ſhall abide much paine &amp; torment in hel, when yet the body ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſléepeth quiet in the graue, expecting his woeful reſurrection.</p>
            <p>And now of the ſecond death, which Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Matt. 10.28</note> and our Apoſtle Iohn cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth hell, &amp; the lake of fire. <hi>Feare not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaith Chriſt, which kill the body, but are not able to kill the ſoule: but rather feare him which is able to deſtroy both body &amp; ſoule, into hel.</hi> Here is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the firſt death; &amp; the death of the ſoule in hell, the ſecond. Of the ſame ſeconde death, ſpeaketh S. Iohn in this receiued text. Goe too, you worldlings,<note place="margin">Iam. 5.1. Rom. 2.5.</note> that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vp wrath to your ſelues, for the laſt day: tribulation and anguiſh, death and hell, ſhall be your portion. Looke to this
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8971:26"/> you ſcorners y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> put far off the laſt day, here is to you endles woe. You haue made a couenant with death, but death it ſelfe and hell, viz. the damned ſoules in them, ſhall henceforth be caſt both bodie and ſoule, into the burning lake of fire &amp; brimſton, which is the ſecond death. For be the day neuer ſo long, at the laſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth Euening. Oh, beloued that wéepe nowe, then ſhall you laugh and reioyce, if ſo that you kiſſe &amp; embrace the Sonne of God, &amp; fal before his preſence, conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your ſelues for ſin, &amp; killing ſinn in you, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of his ſpirit you ſhal the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſée y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proud antechriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pharaoh, &amp; al his popiſh Egyptia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, caſt into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea &amp; gulfe of vnquenchable fire, when your ſelues, by your mighty Moſes &amp; captain chriſt, ſhall be ledd into the heauenly lande of promiſe, there to raigne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him for euer &amp; euer. Many men mooue much diſpute about the ſite and place of hell, this firie lake: But I ſay onely this of it: It is a forbidden curioſitie, engendring ſtrife, deuoide of profit, to queſtion where, and in what place it is: But it is a comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded diuinitie, to ſéeke the liuing God, with reuerent feare, by his mercie, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:8971:26"/> Chriſtes merite to be raunſomed from the paines and power thereof. Of whoſe power, we thus ſay: The ſecond death (which is hell) hath a double power or prerogatiue. The firſt is a prerogatiue to receiue ſuch perſons as of right doe belong vnto her. The ſeconde is, perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to kéepe their ſoules in that lake, till the day of iudgement, and can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be coniured or commaunded to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer any one of them (or can they come out of her) by any authoritie or power, of Pope or whole papaſie: but after that day, ſhall poſſeſſe both the bodies &amp; ſouls of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> malignant Church, to her euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting tormentes. Nowe, what ſoules and perſons, doe belong to her, our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doth tel vs, in the <hi>21.</hi> of this book, ſaying: <hi>But the fearefull and vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and the abhominable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 21.8.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, &amp; whormongers, &amp; idolaters &amp; ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers, &amp; al liers, ſhal haue their part in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lake, which burneth with fire &amp; brimſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is the ſecond death.</hi> Thrée ſortes of perſons Gods ſpirit doeth aſſure vs, to be vnder the power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond death. That is: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obſtinate Infidell, the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Papiſte, and the abhominable
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:8971:27"/> couetous of the worlde: as drunkards whoremongers, murtherers, couetous, liars and ſuch like. Delicate be your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes, yee gallants of theſe dayes, but wiſely call them to account, before the mourners followe the ſinfull corps to the graue.<note place="margin">Eccle. 12.1. &amp;c.</note> For if the Lord (which is the ſearcher of the heart) find your delights with death to end in infidelitie, in feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full poperie, or in any theſe carnal abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deceiue not your ſelues: for the prerogatiue of the ſecond death, may not be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her. God is a iuſt God,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.6.</note> and in his iuſtice, will iudge euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to the verie nature of his worke. Note here alſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ciuill honeſtie, without Chriſts diuinitie, cannot kéepe the honeſt Infidel, and vnbeléeuer, from the ſecond death. For we poſſeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, by inheritance onely, and we are none otherwiſe made heires, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by this prerogatiue, that we are made the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns of God.<note place="margin">Io. 1.</note> And wee are none otherwiſe made the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of God, but by our faith in Ieſus Chriſt. Nor can this faith bée elſe obtained, but by the ſpirite of God. Or doth this ſpirit otherwiſe (ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily) worke it in vs, then by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:8971:27"/> of the word of God. But, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell reiecteth the worde:<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.5.</note> and therefore Gods ſpirite: likewiſe our Chriſt, and in him, our heauenly father, and ſo fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, this heauenly inheritance. And as for our honeſt life and good workes, they ſerue, but ſo ſeale vp the heartes of the faithfull, to thaſſuraunce of their electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to procure others, to prayſe the Lorde, being benefited by them, in vs. But the onely hand that apprehendeth our inheritance in Chriſt, is our firme fixed faith in him, beléeuing by his word and ſpirit, in the full conſent of our har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, that he is the ſame, which the moſt mercifull father hath giuen him to be to vs: That is, our wiſedome, our iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, our holyneſſe, our frée and moſt abſolute redemption:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.10.</note> and ſo in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of our heartes, doe by faith em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace him.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> The ſecond ſort ſubiect vnto hel, are the feareful papiſtes, who ſhal neuer (ſo dying) eſcape y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond death. And if you will marke with me this Epitheton, <hi>fearefull:</hi> &amp; therewith meaſure in truth, the popiſh profeſſion: you muſt of méere neceſſitie grant me, that no papiſt (dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8971:28"/> in his popery) can be elſe where pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced but in the ſecond death. And to your better vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding hereof, you muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt feare &amp; feare: for there is a feare, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to vs, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptures,<note place="margin">Pſa. 111.10.</note> as: <hi>The feare of the Lord is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of wiſedom:</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,<note place="margin">Pſa. 2.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>Serue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde in feare, &amp; reioyce to him with tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling.</hi> Again, <hi>Feare god, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor the king,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>loue brotherly fellowſhip.</hi> But this is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> feare, which Gods ſpirite planteth in his children, to ſerue him in his true worſhip, &amp; is euer ioyned, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured knowledge, &amp; affiance in God. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knot of chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mariage,<note place="margin">Pſal. 58.9. Pſal. 112. Pſal. 118.</note> this ſacred feare is rightly ſhadowed: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wife fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to offend her huſband, but it is for reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; loue to him, &amp; neuer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance of his fauor, becauſe ſhe knoweth him, to be her maried huſband: So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly child, doth feare to diſpleaſe his father, not bicauſe he doubteth of his loue, but for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would not gréeue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of his life, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he feleth moſt aſſured<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in natural knot, faſt tyed to him. And though his father lend him a frowning face, he knows y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe his lookes proceed of fatherly loue, to his correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. wherof
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:8971:28"/> perſuaded, ſo he feareth, ſo he truſteth, ſo he naturally loueth &amp; obeieth him. And this knowledge &amp; loue driueth away fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy feare, which gendreth painefulnes. But the feare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iohn ſpeaketh of, is flat contrarie to this. It is begotten by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt in god, it is borne of ignorance, it liueth to diſpaire, &amp; dieth in gret painful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. what other is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole profeſſion of popery, but méere timiditie? They euer diſtruſt god of his promiſe, during their life, &amp; therefore they die in feare of his fauor, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houre of death. If he ſay: <hi>That ſoule y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſinneth ſhal die,</hi> they beleue him not, but walke fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin to ſin, committing more truſt to a Popes bul, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> credit to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> immortal word of god. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſay, and ſweare alſo: <hi>Verely, verely,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. 5.24.</note> 
               <hi>he that heareth my words, &amp; beleueth in him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſent me, hath euerlaſting life, &amp; ſhall not come into conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but hath paſſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death to life.</hi> yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſt is afraid to reſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this promiſe: for he doth not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely beléeue it, but is in feare notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after death, his ſoule ſhal go to condemnation, if not to hell, yet at the leaſt to purgatory. Though the ſpirit of God ſay, <hi>There is no conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:8971:29"/> that are graft in Chriſt Ieſu: whoſe life is not after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, but after the ſpirit:</hi> yet the papiſt, wil not beleeue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ought to be aſſured of this Chriſtian rocke, to reſt vpon: but caſteth himſelfe into the raging ſea of wauering diſtruſt. Which feareful perſuaſion, hath béene the very building of al Abbies, priories, &amp; popiſh paultries, from many yeres paſt vs, and doth bréede great blaſphemie to the glorie of God. For firſt it taketh away the foundation of our faith, in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of Chriſt, which is, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God almighty is become our father in him, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is nowe well pleaſed with vs, and as a father, not onely doeth pardon our ſins, but ſo tenderly loueth vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities whatſoeuer, he carefully helpeth. It taketh away alſo this holy boldnes in loue, which his ſpirit doeth aſſure vs of, and Chriſt doeth teach vs to cry vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him:<note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> 
               <hi>O thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> art our father.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the popiſh doubtfulnes taketh away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefite of Chriſt his ſonne. For we are taught to beleue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt is dead, for vs, that he is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lambe of God, which taketh away our ſinnes, that nothing can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne vs, becauſe our Chriſt hath iuſtified
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:8971:29"/> vs, and is deade, riſen againe, and ſet at the right hand of God, for vs, ſo that in him, we that truely beléeue, are more then conquerours: ſo as neither hell or heauen, man or Angel, prince or diuell, things preſent or to come, can ſeparate vs, from our benefite, and loue of Chriſt. This certaintie the booke of God doth teach vs: but from this anchorholde, the diuell and poperie, laboureth to drawe vs. Thirdly it taketh all godly conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from vs, in the day of tentation, &amp; layeth vs open to Sathans iawes. For who can lift vp his heart, in tentation, that fighting with his enimy much ſtronger the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he, hath no hope of his cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Chriſt, the ſtrongeſt of all, or in the mercie of God, to defende him? It al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo taketh away ardent &amp; earneſt prayer to God: for who can with comfort crie in triall, that ſtandeth in feare he ſhall not be hearde? but in the ende he falleth into diſpaire &amp; hate of God, to all looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life, and ruffianlike boldnes, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king luſt to liue in ſinne, not expecting other then hell at the ende. Laſte of all, the popiſh doctrine of doubtfulneſſe figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth flat againſt the nature of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:8971:30"/> faith: which is not a light opinion of our God, and Chriſt his loue to vs, and our ſaluation in him: but a moſt firme, ſtable and ſure foundation ſetled in our ſoules: ſo, as neither fire in earth, nor powers in hell, can burne or raze it out of our heartes, that wee are ſealed by his ſpirite, in the faith of his Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> to be his children, and fellowe heires with our eldeſt brother Chriſt our Lorde, in his great loue, wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath loued vs, yea, euen when we were his enimies. Wherefore we are taught that bee faithfull,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> to holde this for moſt certaine: that though wee be wicked of our ſelues, yet are wee iuſtified by his grace, in our faith, and haue peace with God, and frée acceſſe in one ſpirite, to God our father nowe, and ſhalbe recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to him of Angels, when we departe this life, as this our text doth alſo tell vs. Hell ſhall not touch vs, but we ſhall raigne with God, his prieſtes, and holy ones for euer. Caſt off popiſh feareful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe therfore, &amp; acquaint your ſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the hearing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God: ſo ſhal yée learne, to be firme in faith &amp; ſure to liue. Here be touched alſo, all thoſe, which
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:8971:30"/> feare men rather then God, and in time of perſecution runne from religion, or in the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of popiſh princes, iudges, tormentours, or before a balde Maſſe-prieſt, dare not confeſſe the Lorde: but to ſaue his momentary life, doth caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the eternall. <hi>Hee that will ſaue his life, ſhall loſe it:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 10.38. Mark. 8.35 Luk. 9.23. Io. 12.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; he that ſhal loſe his life for my ſake and the goſpels, ſhall ſaue it, ſaith our ſauiour Chriſt.</hi> Pray, pray: pray the Lorde to pull you out of poperie (beloued) and in ſpeede, come out of Babilon,<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.</note> which is appointed to be caſt into the fierie lake, leaſt being parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of her ſinnes, yée alſo féede of her plagues. The thirde ſort which ſhall to hell, are the abhominable murtherers, harlots, and ſuch like. Theſe abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are to be vnderſtoode of ſuch perſons, as, hauing once profeſſed the trueth of God, are now, not onely become to hate it, but moſt filthily they blaſpheme it, perſecute and torment thoſe, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it, to whom is reſerued fire &amp; brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone. Heb. 6. Heb. 10. The reſt, are ſo manifeſt, as néede no commentarie: onely let vs knowe, that murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers be they, which kill, wound or hurt,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:8971:31"/> themſelues or their neighbours, either with the ſworde of an hateful heart,<note place="margin">1. Io. 3.15.</note> (as Iohn ſaith) or with the ſharpned tongue (as Dauid ſaith) or with the hande, as Caine did his brother Habell.<note place="margin">Pſa. 120.3.4</note> And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not that the ſeconde death, is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle for all ſuch as die impenitent hereof.</p>
            <p>The ſeconde parte of deathes power in hell is, faſt to retaine her captiues, from the houre of their death with Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, vntil the day of the laſt reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: which thing is moſt plainely proued by the ſtorie of Diues and Lazarus.<note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe (beloued) the papiſts graunt with vs, that in the hels there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: but they ſay, that in the earth there are diſtinct, thrée ſorts of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: One ſort moſt holy, another ſort moſt wicked and the thirde ſort of a certain mixture, neither ſo holy, as ſtraight vpon death they demerite to goe to heauen, or yet ſo wicked, as at all they can be ſent to hell, but are for a time, committed after death, vnto the paines of Purgatorie, and muſt thence bée delyuered, not by mercie, but by merite of Maſſes (dirtie) diriges, popes (paltries called) pardons,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:8971:31"/> and ſuch like. And here is your founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and your cauſe of prayer for the deade. In aunſwere wherof we graunt: ſome perſons are ſo ſanctified in earth, that ſtraight from hence they goe to heauen, but not for any their merite: For they are taught to holde, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing done all they can:<note place="margin">Luke 17.10.</note> yet they are none other but waſting and vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruauntes. And that ſome are ſo wicked, that ſtraight they goe to hell, as all obſtinate, rebellyous and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous papiſtes, feareful wretches, and abhominable perſons, we firmely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue. But, that there are any ſo imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that for their imperfection, they are ſtayed from heauen, and for their rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of holyneſſe, cannot come to hell, and therefore of neceſſitie muſt tumble into a popiſh purgatorie, this we flatly affirme to be a fooliſh opinion, without warrant from God. And touching theſe mixed perſons, ſurely the Church neither hath had, or ſhall haue any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Of women: was not that moſt holy maide, Marie, the bleſſed mother of Chriſt, one moſt ſacred?<note place="margin">Io. 2.3.4.</note> But both the holy ſcriptures, and her owne confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:8971:32"/> conuinceth her of ſinne, but ſhe is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by her Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.</note> ſaying: <hi>My ſpirit doth reioyce in God my ſauiour.</hi> And for her daily ſinnes, ſhe, as al other, is taught to pray: forgiue vs our ſinnes. So alſo, in her bleſſed bodie, was ſure faith, great loue, a pure heart, and much godlyneſſe, wherefore beholde a certaine mixture. Alſo of men: the Apoſtles were the moſt pure, and yet not without the bodies of ſinne. What elſe moueth Paul, to crie to the Romans:<note place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> 
               <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of this death?</hi> And this our moſt holie Iohn, in his firſt Epiſtle, doth accuſe himſelfe,<note place="margin">1. Io. 1.8.</note> &amp; all other Apoſtles, of ſin, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>If we ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue no ſinne, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue our ſelues, &amp;c.</hi> Thus they liued, &amp; thus they dyed with this battel againſt ſinne, but had victorie in Ieſus Chriſt. Yet I trow, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the papiſtes will not ſay: how the gratious virgin Mary and the holy Apoſtles, went from death, to their popiſh purgatorie.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.23.</note> The ſame mixture, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, in one bodie, to haue obeying faith, &amp; in it another lawe rebelling to the ſpirite, is in all the electe of God, in more or leſſe meaſure. By meanes
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:8971:32"/> whereof, there cannot but bee many ſharpe battels, in the hearte of man, ſo, as ſome times, he ſlippeth &amp; is brought very low, &amp; ſomtimes he reſteth againe and taketh courage, and ſtoutly ſtandeth vnder the banner, of his captain Chriſt, by the ſtrength of his holy ſpirite: but yet at the houre of death, if he ſhoulde be meaſured, by his falls, he ſhould be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged worthy of the ſecond death.<note place="margin">Pſal. 130.3.</note> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath his part (by true &amp; louing Faith, in repentance) of the firſt reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, he dyeth bleſſed in the Lord, and holy, reſteth from his labours in earth, and paines in hell: for, the ſecond death hath no power of him, much leſſe can a popiſh purgatorie, which is not. I come not to diſpute with the papiſtes nowe, but to lay forth the plaine doctrine of ſaluation, to your Chriſtian hearts, and ſomething to let you ſée the blindnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſide, which in ſo cléere a light do grope at their owne inuentions. But to your purgatory thus much: Is there ſuch a place? yea ſir. I pray you wher ſir, haue you warrant for it in the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? Forſooth ſaith the papiſt, both in the olde Teſtament, and in the newe.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8971:33"/> doth not Zacharie ſay:<note place="margin">Zach. 9.11.</note> 
               <hi>I haue looſed my priſoners out of the pitte wherein is no water?</hi> Sir, here is our purgatory. Well proued: and like the reſt of all your religion. Héere is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion made of a pitte voide of water, &amp; that is ynough for purgatories proofe. Such warrant haue they, for the aſſumption of their Lady, hauing no warrant for it, in their blaſphemous Maſſe, of that day they ſolemnely ſing the Goſpel, of Marie &amp; Martha. But this is ynough to blinde the eyes of the ignorant, that they haue the name of Marie, in that Maſſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it concerne a farre other matter, and be altogether ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of another per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And euen ſuch is the popiſh begge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of this rich place, and promiſe of Gods prophet here. But be it that this ſcripture did any whitte toote at your purgatorie: I pray you ſir, hath your purgatorie neither fire nor water in it? you ſée, water is here denied, and here is no mention of fire at all. Beſides, the deliuerie here is ſaide to be, by the Lorde in heauen, and that in his mercy, without their merite: But out of your purgatorie, mens ſoules are deliuered
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:8971:33"/> by men: in earth, without him in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, through their merite (to his iuſtice) of prayer and almes, and diriges, and reſtles maſſes, and ſuch like, and not by his mercie. And for the proofe hereof, you cite this place:<note place="margin">Matt. 5.26.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall not come out thence, till hee hath paide the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt farthinge.</hi> If this ſentence ſerue your purpoſe, then this doctrin, is right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gathered of it, that though all the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in the worlde pray and crie, and launce themſelues,<note place="margin">1. King. 18 27.</note> with their forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the falſe prieſtes of Baal, till they ceaſe to liue, yet their poore popiſh priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner lyeth in the pitte ſtill, but without fire or water, (it is ſure, ſome driefatte) till he hath payed, &amp; not prayed, the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt farthing. Thus (beloued) yée may ſée what gaine the papiſtes haue got of this place, which they haue ſtollen from his true ſenſe, to ſhadowe their ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full briberie, and marchandize of mens ſoules in a faigned purgatorie. If it bée lawfull to allegorize this place,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.1.2.3 Apoc. 12.16.17.</note> then this lake is rather the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, &amp; the bloude of the couenaunt, is the death of the Lord Chriſt: who hath long ſince, before we were borne, purged vs,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:8971:34"/> and thence deliuered vs,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oll. 1.13.</note> and hath tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated vs into the kingdome of himſelfe. And your owne doctour Hierome affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this lake is (not purgatory, but) hell it ſelf. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true ſenſe of the place is, an aſſurance of Gods hande to them of Ieruſalem, for the couenant of his Chriſt, for whoſe ſake hee hath nowe brought them from Babylons bondage.</p>
            <p>A ſecond place, the papiſtes haue of the new Teſtament, &amp; that is out of the <hi>1.</hi> Corinth. <hi>3. Euerie mans worke ſhall be made manifeſt: for the day ſhall declare it, becauſe it ſhalbe reuealed by the fire, &amp; the fire ſhal trie euery mans worke, of what ſort it is.</hi> And this place ſéemeth ſo flatte on their ſide, that néedes we muſt haue a purgatorie.<note place="margin">Aeneid 6. Olimp. 2. Aretius loc. 56.</note> Truely, for all this, we muſt driue them to Virgil, &amp; Pinda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, for Paul doth no whit helpe them. And (good Chriſtian auditorie) meaſure their opinion, by this ſcripture, and you ſhall ſée howe falſely they father their purgatorie hereof. Héerein is mention of fire, I graunt: But ſuch is this fire, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not the perſons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do work gold or ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> work wrought ſhalbe caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it: For he ſaith, <hi>&amp; the fire ſhal trie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:8971:34"/> mans worke, &amp;c.</hi> but they are to proue a place of fire, wherein the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for his worke, is to be caſt, which thou ſeeſt cannot be this. Againe, they ſay no man ſhal come into their purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mixed ſort wherof we ſpake before: But Paul ſpeaketh here, of ſuch a fire, as vniuerſally all muſt be tryed by. For he ſaith not, they which haue builded haye, woode or ſtubble only, ſhal be tryed there, but alſo they, which haue builded golde, ſiluer, &amp; precious ſtones vpon the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation: Theſe good workme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt yet goe through this fire, or at the leaſt their workemanſhippe: For hee ſaith, <hi>euery mans worke, &amp;c.</hi> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the texte doth not ſaye, that this fire ſhall purge the worke from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, or chaunge it: as to make Haye become Golde; Woode, Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer; ſtubble precious ſtones: But hée ſaith, it ſhall bee <hi>ignis probatorius, non Purgatorius,</hi> it ſhall onelye prooue and trye, what nature the mettall is off, not purge the perſon; or his worke at all. Doe not yee ſée, by this ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and ſhort ſifting of their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe follyes, with this portion of holye
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:8971:35"/> ſcripture, that the papiſts are ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous robbers of God, and his ſcriptures? I doubt not, but you doe. Adde to this, their owne doctors are of other iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, touching this fire. Chriſoſtome ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it for hell fire:<note place="margin">To. 1. li. 4. c. 36</note> Hierome, for the fire at the laſt day, which ſhal then trie eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans worke what it is: Gregorie a Pope of Rome, vnderſtandeth it for the afflictions of this life: And auncient Ambroſe interpreteth it of doctrine, which of al other is the néereſt the mind of the Apoſtle. For, the Apoſtle ſpeaketh only of preachers &amp; their labours, which the fire of Gods iudgement ſhall make manifeſt at his appointed ſeaſon, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they haue preached with the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Religion in truth, and taught other points of doctrine alſo, ſincerely &amp; ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in puritie of trueth, or more corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue laide erronious opinions; vpon the foundation of our faith. This was the Apoſtles purpoſe, ſo that if this fire ſhoulde be of purgatorie, then no man, but preachers, (proteſtantes and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh) ſhoulde come thither. Laſt of all, their tranſgreſſions coulde neuer in this fire bée forgiuen, but onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:8971:35"/> ſuch as they were. But if they could haue ſo good happe, as there to bée purged, yet is mercie ſo ſhutte out of that purgatorie, that no prayer can obtaine remiſſion of ſinnes there, or any redemption, can bee had, till ſufficient paines be paide in that ſcarrefire, and ſo by fire, the ſoule muſt bee purged. Some other places they bring out, for their purgatorie. As,<note place="margin">Macha. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that acte of Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beus for the dead, who ſent his ſiluer to pray for them, and is commended by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abridgement. For anſwere heereto, I ſay, althoughe we ſhoulde graunt this Act conſonant w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the word (which indéed, is moſt flat againſt it) yet, that he, in that corruption of the Churche, prayed for the dead, nothing ſhall it proue for your purgatorie, no more then the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of ſome auncientes before vs, for the dead, did, when as they dreamed, not of purgatorie, but thought onely of the reſurrection,<note place="margin">verſ. 44.</note> as Iudas doth in this place. But I ſay to this place, as ſome Lawyers vſe to ſay: Truth may not be trodden vnderfoote with a counterfaite ſhowe. Of the weakenes of this booke, the Papiſtes themſelues ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:8971:36"/> knowe, and he that is ignorant thereof, let him read Kemniſius againſt the Tridentine councel in his <hi>Hiſtoria Purgatorii, cap. 20. ſeſſ. <hi>8.</hi>
               </hi> I will no longer detaine you (good people) in theſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie matters: onely I tell you, ſuch warrant hath all the reſt of their profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for their imagined purgatory, out of which they ſay mens ſoules ſhal once come, but they know not when. No, no, the ſeconde death is the onely receptacle of them, that goe not to heauen, where they ſhalbe holden remedileſſe vntill the laſt reſurrection. And this is the power of the ſecond death. Againſt this the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes alſo ſay, that after life there is forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, to this mixed companye, which is obtained by their friendes, and merites of the Church, for them. But (beloued) this is their dreame againſt the trueth of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the iudgementes of their beſt doctours, both which affirme plainely, that after naturall death, there is no remiſſion of ſinnes to the departed. Wherfore Dauid (in his life time) pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.13.</note> 
               <hi>O Lorde ſtay thine anger from mee, that I may recouer my ſtrength before I
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:8971:36"/> goe hence, and be not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The parable of the wiſe,<note place="margin">Matth. 25.</note> and fooliſhe virgin, is ſet downe of Chriſt to proue this. and howe fareth it with them? The wiſer ſort take Oyle with them: They loue, and liue a Chriſtian life, while they haue time in this world, and therefore <hi>their owne workes doe follow them:</hi> and preſent themſelues, as a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the parties faith, and are crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with mercie: <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father, when I was an hungrie, you fedde mee.</hi> But the fooliſhe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, though of the ſame calling, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, the ſame profeſſion to beare the lampe: Yet, becauſe they were careleſſe of Gods holy ſpirite, and thereby had no lightes before men, of Godly labours in good woorkes (the true triall of a liuelye faith) but haue committed that vnto their friendes, for them. Theſe (I ſay) wanting true obedience to GOD, who hath ſaide,<note place="margin">Matt. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, that they ſeeing your good workes, may glorie your Father which is in Heauen,</hi> had a boundance of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalitie, with them.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:8971:37"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.24.</note> Theſe their euill workes, as ſome went before, and ſome followed them, vnto Iudgmente: ſo, they (after life) coulde haue none other anſwere to their crie,<note place="margin">Matt. 25.13</note> 
               <hi>(Lorde open to vs)</hi> but this: <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte ye curſed, I know you not.</hi> As many of you, heere preſent, therefore, as longe after life: ſéeke the Lord while he is to be founde, before your naturall death. While ye haue the light (ſaith Chriſt our Lorde) walke in the light: For darkneſſe will come, wherein no man can walke. And his Apoſtle Paul ſaith,<note place="margin">Galat. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>While wee haue time, let vs doe good to all men:</hi> but he ſaith, while we haue time, which time is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we poſſeſſe in this life, and not others for vs after it. To this doctrine the auncient wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſubſcribe their heartes, and haue left their handes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, yea euen ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſts approue for ſaincts, &amp; their writings equall to the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>And firſt touching the ſentence of Dauid before cited, videlicet: <hi>Lorde ſtaye thine anger from mee. &amp;c.</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe<note place="margin">Ambroſius To. 1. li de B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Mor. c. 2. pag. 243</note> ſaith, <hi>Qui enim hic non accipit, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truely he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> receiueth not forgiuenes
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:8971:37"/> of his ſinnes, in this life, ſhall not bée there. He ſhal not be there. Why? for hee can not poſſibly come to eternall life, becauſe life eternall dependeth v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the forgiuenes of ſinnes. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Dauid prayed, <hi>Forgiue me Lorde, that I may bee comforted, before I goe hence.</hi> Thus farre Ambroſe. Hierome a prieſt of Rome, and one of the foure Euangeliſtes of that Synagogue, vpon the ſame text, writing vpon Eſay, ſaith:<note place="margin">Hier. in Eſa. to. 5. cap. 65 Pa. 244. b.</note> 
               <hi>He that whileſt he heere liueth, <hi>Dum in hoc corpore viuit</hi>) hath not obteined for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of his ſinnes, but hath without ſuch remiſſion, departed this life, hee periſheth to God, and ceaſſeth to bee: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he continue to himſelf, in paine and tormentes.</hi> And as touching the ſeconde ſcripture: <hi>Dum tempus habemus,</hi> Hierome ſaith of it: <hi>This our preſent life, is the ſeede time for vs to ſowe, whatſoeuer we wil</hi> (ſaith Hierome:) <hi>but when this life is paſſed, and gone from vs, then is the time of good working taken away alſo.</hi> Auguſtine ſaith here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>In futuro ſolism eſt remuneratio, <hi>In the life to come there is onely recompence and condemnation: but in this life, our
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:8971:38"/> ſinnes are either bounde vp or looſed.</hi>
               </hi> And that learned Cyprian ſaith expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>When our departure ſhall be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hence, there is lefte no place for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance or power of any ſatisfaction.</hi> No ſaith Auguſtine <hi>ad Heſichium:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ad He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. To. 2. epi. 80. fol. 350.</note> 
               <hi>For in what ſtate ſoeuer at the laſt day of mans life, death ſhall ſinde him: in the ſame ſtate and condition, the laſt day of the worlde, ſhall comprehende him. <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam qualis in die iſto quiſque moritur, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis in illo die iudicabitur:</hi> For in what caſe ſoeuer a man at his laſt day, ſhall die, in the ſame caſe and ſtate, ſhall the Lord iudge him, at the great day.</hi> From all theſe places, and witneſſes then (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) yee ſée, that neither popiſh prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Romiſhe maſſes, deadly diriges, friuolous almes, or paltrie pardons, paines in purgatorie, or popiſhe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons can any whit alter the ſtate &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the perſons once dead: but ſuch workes as they themſelues caried with them, ſuch ſhall they riſe withall vnto their iudgement: whether lampes of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing faith, to the praiſe of God, or creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſettes of corruption, to their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. And thus I will conclude,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:8971:38"/> with the ſpirite of Gods ſentence, our beſt moderator, and ſo paſſe to the laſt braunch.<note place="margin">Io. 5.28.</note> 
               <hi>Maruell not at this</hi> (ſayth Chriſte) <hi>for the houre ſhall come, in the which all that are in the graues, ſhall heare his voice: And they ſhall come forth, that haue done good vnto the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of life: But they that haue done euill, vnto the reſurrection of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> The ſame aſſurance of doctrine, Gods ſpirite, by Paul doeth deliuer vs ſaying:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>We muſt all appeare before the iudgement ſeate of Chriſte, that euery man may receiue the thinges which are done in his bodye, according to that hee hath done, whether it bee good or euill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note well this doctrine, and amend your liues, reſt not vppon the doubtfull doctrine, of poperie (O dearely bought children of GOD) but fixe your faith, in this abſolute doctrine of ſound warrant, which is yea, and amen Then here you may perceiue, that after death there is no <hi>temporarie priſon,</hi> as <hi>Popiſh purgatorie</hi> but a perpetuall lake of fire, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond death: And alſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after this life, there is no remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſins to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:8971:39"/> that hath not obteined that grace, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this time of repentance. But euen in what ſtate the ſoule departeth from the bodie, at the comming of death: euen vnchanged, hee retyreth to the ſame bodie at the laſt, for the déeds done by himſelfe, and not for the workes of any other done after him: And to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue his iudgement, whether through faith (in her fruites) vnto life, in Chriſt, or becauſe of ſinne and Sathan, to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death. This is the ſound, and ſure doctrine of our good God. But as for the gainefull and paineful preaching of poperie, and her purgatorie, as a moſt venemous Serpente, flée from it: that you may eſcape the ſeconde death, and be partakers of the felicitie of the iuſt, which our text ſaith, is this: <hi>For they ſhall bee the prieſtes of God and Chriſt, and ſhall raigne with him a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande yeares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cicero hath ſaide, that true beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude or bleſſedneſſe conſiſteth of two partes: Namely, to be frée from al kinde of want and miſerie: and ſo to abound in all goodneſſe, that on no parte he née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to aſke further. Surely this very
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:8971:39"/> happineſſe ſhall come to all thoſe, which be partakers of the firſt reſurrection. Firſt, they ſhall be frée from all woe and miſerie, in the ende of their courſe: for the ſeconde death, ſhall haue no power of them. And they ſhall abounde in all felicitie: for they are bleſſed, &amp; holy, and ſhall therefore raigne with Chriſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more. And here againe (beloued) note with me, what it is, to be bleſſed and holy. Namely, to haue forgiuenes of our ſinnes in Chriſtes death:<note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> and by the ſame, to be purged and ſegregated from dead workes, to ſerue the liuing God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.1.2. Rom. 4.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are they</hi> (ſaith Dauid) <hi>whoſe iniquities are forgiuen, &amp; whoſe ſinnes are couered: bleſſed is the man to whome the Lorde doeth not impute ſinne.</hi> And then againe note, who they be that are ſo bleſſed, by Gods cenſure here: marke it wel, and thou ſhalt ſée it: Not they, that liue ſo vprightly, that God hath not any thing, to lay to their charges: for none ſuch can be founde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the ſonnes of men. For what is he, that liueth and ſinneth not, yea, more then ſeauen times a day?<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1. &amp; 53.4.</note> No fleſh is righteous in Gods ſight: for all haue
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:8971:40"/> ſinned,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.23.</note> all haue gone out of the way, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man his ſeuered courſe: this, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this ſinne, another, after that, and all are therefore depriued of the glory of God:<note place="margin">Dan. 9.5.</note> All are taught to cry, <hi>We &amp; our fathers haue ſinned, wee haue done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly, but deale not with vs, O Lord, in thine anger, for then wee periſhe: but in the multitude of thy mercies, haue thou mercie vpon vs, and forgiue vs our treſpaſſes.</hi> And heerein conſiſteth the felicitie of the iuſt, that they haue féeling heartes of ſinne, and penitent ſpirites for their tranſgreſſions: hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſoules, void of hypocriſie, before the Almightie God, confeſſing with teares, in great remorſe &amp; agonies, their heaps of corruptions, before him: Euen Marie Chriſtes mother, the Apoſtles and all the foure electe of God. Then are theſe mixed perſons (whome the Papiſtes make the thirde ſorte, to goe to purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie) onely they which are bleſſed, and are the whole number of the electe. All which as they confeſſe them ſelues; worthie the ſeconde death, becauſe of Sinne, and no wayes can merite eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, becauſe their beſte workes
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:8971:40"/> are full of corruption: So they migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily triumphe ouer ſinne,<note place="margin">Eſa. 30.22.</note> death and hell: becauſe they are purged in the bloode of the lambe,<note place="margin">Reuel. 7.14.</note> and haue their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes made white, are pardoned, of their former ſinnes, by faith, in hys bloode, &amp; are ſanctified vnto godlineſſe. Yea, ſo long as they liue, they confeſſe: becauſe they féele the burthen of ſinne in them, but they reioyce in this fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie, that his ſpirite worketh in them an ardent zeale, and burninge deſire, to liue in godlineſſe and honeſtie, according to ſuch portion, as the Lord doeth giue them, in their parte of the firſt reſurrection. And hee that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not this, nor hath the practiſe of the premiſſes, is blinde and hath forgotten the purgation of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, forget not, this our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doth not ſay, <hi>Bleſſed is he,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>which hath perfection in the firſte reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> but, <hi>bleſſed is hee, that hath hys part in the firſt reſurrection.</hi> So as, though there bee in vs, yet the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes of ſinne, and we can not quite ſhake off, that which cleaueth ſo faſte
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:8971:41"/> on,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> or fully créepe, from that burthen, that preſſeth ſo harde vpon vs: (&amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alwayes of this ſort, that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called mixt) yet that Mediocritie or mixture, can not ſende vs to the ſecond death, if we haue our part, in the firſte reſurrection. But I would not leaue thy conſcience to bare affirmations. There be verie ſounde reaſons to drawe thy confidence to this comforte.<note place="margin">1. Reaſon.</note> The firſte is, the great mercie and rich clemencie of God the father, whoſe mercie hath béene ſuch towardes vs, that when wée were his enemies, through ſinne, hee hath euen then reconciled vs to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by his grace: howe much more therefore nowe, ſhall he eſtéeme vs for his, and embrace vs with his armes of mercie, ſéeing, we being ſo reconciled, ſéeke for his ſpirite to dwell in his loue? If hee from his wrath deliuered vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we had no care of him: ſhal he not much more nowe deliuer vs, ſhew a parte thereof (which they ſay, is purgatorie) nowe that our chiefe deſire is, to ſéeke after him: and doe lament, at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie heart, that dayly we ſo grieue him by our ſinne? This I take to be Pauls
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:8971:41"/> comfort to vs, where he ſaith: <hi>But God ſetteth out his loue towardes vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.8.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeing that while we were yet ſinners, Chriſte died for vs: much more then, being now iuſtified by his bloode, wee ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from wrath, through him. For, if when we were enemies, we were recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God, by the death of his ſonne: much more, being reconciled, wee ſhall be ſaued by his life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſeconde argument is of the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute ſacrifice of Chriſt, Gods ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, for vs. we cannot fall from naturall death, into popiſh purgatorie, which are graft into his death: for the ſame hath fully ſatiſfied the iuſtice of God for vs, paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied his anger, and obteined vs eternall redemption.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.18.</note> For <hi>Chriſt alſo hath once ſuffered</hi> (ſaith Peter,) <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſt for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt, that he might (not ſende vs to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie, but) bring vs to God.</hi> And this Chriſt in his owne bodie, bare our ſins, on the trée,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24</note> that being deliuered from ſinne (then of good conſequent, from the rewarde of ſinne, which is death) wee ſhoulde liue in righteouſneſſe: by whoſe ſtripes (and not by popiſhe purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries purging) we are ſoundly healed.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:8971:42"/> The fathers wrath, in this ſacrifice, is fully pacified: for he hath giuen vs twice warrant thereof, by his owne voyce, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.24. Mat. 3.17. &amp; 17.5. 1. Pet. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>This is my beloued ſonne in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi> It reſteth therefore, according to our heauenly fathers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, that we onely heare, and beléeue him. No feare of death, or iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to hell, (much leſſe to purgatorie) can come then to vs, which liue in the firſt reſurrection by newnes of life. For the Lorde our redemer, hath payed the full price of our ranſome, and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our <hi>Lutron</hi> and <hi>Lutroſis,</hi> ſo as, the vttermoſt farthing is tendred to Gods iuſtice in his death, for mans ſinne, not by petition of ſparing, or bearing for day of further payment,<note place="margin">Matt. 20.</note> but by his blood he hath paide himſelfe once for all, a full and abſolute price for our redemption, to his father,<note place="margin">Col. 2.14.15</note> and hath therfore, trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed on the croſſe againſt principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and powers, and hath taken vs, in his victorie from the handes of captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp; tranſlated vs into his grace, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out the whole hand writing that was againſt vs. <hi>Totum Chyrographum,</hi> he hath taken away, the whole obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:8971:42"/> not parte of it, in diſcharge of our debts, that be graft in him. And therfore there can not remayne a remnaunt of redemption for our ſelues, in a popiſhe purgatorie: For, to ſuppoſe this, were the greateſt iniurie that coulde be, to the blood of our full ranſome Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſe of Gods mouth which can not lie (whoſe wordes are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes yea, and ſhall be alwayes true, though heauen and earth runne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to perfourme them) is a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſſurance to the conſcience, of the godly man, that hee ſhall paſſe from death, preſently vnto life. For their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie is (ſay they) but to puniſh thoſe ſinnes, which at a mans death, remaine vnpardoned, and not purged before. But to the penitent God ſaith thus: <hi>At what time ſo euer a ſinner doeth repent him of his ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 18.</note> 
               <hi>from the bottome of his heart, at that time will I (ſaith the Lord) I,</hi> (ſhall the Pope then puniſh?) <hi>put all,</hi> (and not part of) <hi>his wickedneſſe out of my remembraunce.</hi> And our ſauiour Chriſt,<note place="margin">Io. 6.</note> hath promiſed vs (which is the author of trueth) <hi>He that beleeueth in me, yea, though he were deade, yet ſhal
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:8971:43"/> he liue. And he that beleueth in me, hath euerlaſting life.</hi> Againe, that which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other, is moſt plaine: <hi>Hee that beleueth in mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. 5.24.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall not come into co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: but hath paſſed from death to life.</hi> Héere is plaine pardon and free immunitie, from iudge and gaoler, or <hi>corpus capias,</hi> to bring to the barre, for them that die in the true faith of the Lord: for they are bleſſed and holy, &amp; ſhal not ſée death, but ſhal be preſently taken vp to life, to be the prieſtes of God, and Chriſt, to raign with him for euermore.</p>
            <p>But now to ende this my tedious labor, (O my deare brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) both tyring you, and much toyling my ſelf gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite doth heere tell vs, howe the faithful (whoſe ſinnes,<note place="margin">Pſa. 32.1.2.</note> though they haue many, are not laid to their charge) are ſo farre, from being plunged in a popiſhe purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, that farre contrary they are exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the height of heauen, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the companie of thoſe ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſoules, which daily follow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lambe, and offer vp to God the holy ſacrifice of praiſe and thankesgiuing, for their redemption in the bloude of the Lambe ſaying:<note place="margin">Apoc. 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>Amen. Praiſe and glorie, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:8971:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> wiſdome and thankes, and honour and power, and might be vnto God, for euer more, Amen. Theſe are they, which came out of great tribulations (ſaith the elder vnto Iohn) and haue waſhed their robes white, in the bloud of the Lambe. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are they in the preſence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> throne of God, and ſerue him day and night in his temple, and hee that ſitteth on the Throne will dwel among them.</hi> This is not a paineful purgatorie, for it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>They ſhall hunger no more, neither thirſt any more, neither ſhall the ſunne light on them, neither any heate (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no hott purgatory fire:) for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lamb which is in the midſt of the Throne, ſhall gouerne them, and ſhall lead them vnto the liuely fountaines of waters, and God ſhal wipe al teares away from their eyes.</hi> Behold héere a moſt bleſſed felicitie, god grant vs al that be héere to day, (if it be his bleſſed will) to be partakers hereof. And now ſomthing to ſay of this reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend perſon, whoſe chriſtian corps doth lye yet before vs, according to the truth of his demerit w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> man, &amp; for whoſe ſake, we are héere aſſembled. Somewhat I knew the man my ſelfe: But I am fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:8971:44"/> aſſured of him, by ſuch as doe not fawne, but truly feare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord: That he was according to gods prouidence, born vnto Chriſt, he hath béene trained vp, in Chriſtianity, &amp; mercifully called, from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peſtilent ſinke of popery, and from his firſt féeling of Chriſt, hath euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in heart, embraced true religion, and very comfortably, made confeſſion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole courſe of his life, ſo as his handworking, hath borne good teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of his beléeuing heart: and hath ſo vprightly receiued theſe great bleſſings caſt vnto him of God, that this offer is made by ſuch as it doth moſt concerne: If any man bee able iuſtly to charge him, to haue at any time willingly done wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to him, or by brybery in his office, to haue enriched himſelfe, vppon due proofe hereof, Zacheus tribute ſhall bée paide vnto him: that is, he ſhalbe reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red foure fold. And though this man had his imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſons of god: yet he comfortably felt his beatitude, in his ſauiour Chriſt, euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forgiuenes of his ſins, in the mercy of God, through him: &amp; therefore as he liued a partaker of the firſt reſurrection: ſo hee ended this life
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:8971:44"/> without feare of the ſeconde death. And as he ſaw with holy Symeon, the Lord Chriſt to be onely his ſaluation: So, we may pronounce of him, with good confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that his ſoule doth reſt in peace. And no doubt, it is taken vp of Angels, vnto the mount Syon, the citie of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, the celeſtiall Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.22.</note> and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> companie of innumerable Angels, and to the congregation of the firſt born, which are written in heauen, and to god the iudge of all: and to Ieſus the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the newe Teſtament, and to the bloude of ſprinkling, that ſpeaketh bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things, then that of Habell. For it aſketh vengeance, more forcibly to the wicked, and promiſeth life, and pardon moſt aſſuredly to the ſonnes of GOD. Wherefore to thée our deare father, our ſauiour Chriſt, and the holy ghoſt, thrée perſons diſtinct, but one immortall god, be all glorie, wiſedome, thankes, honor, power and might, for euer more. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>Laudes Deo, per Christum ſeruatorem noſtrum.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
